Finding Aid for George E. Bushnell papers, 1921-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George E. Bushnell papers 1921-1965
Bushnell, George E. (George Edward), 1887-1965.
13 linear feet
85548 Aa 2
Justice on the Michigan Supreme Court, official in Scottish Rite Freemasonry, Sovereign Grand Commander, Supreme Council, Northern Jurisdiction. Correspondence and other topical files largely relating to activities and offices held within Scottish Rite Freemasonry.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by George E. Bushnell (donor no. 4336 ).
The collection is open to research.
George Edward Bushnell was born November 4, 1887 in Roanoke, Virginia. After graduating from Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1907, and working for a time as an advertising executive, Bushnell studied law in Cincinnati, then came to Detroit in 1913 where he enrolled in the Detroit College of Law. He graduated in 1915, and was admitted first to the Bar of Virginia and later to the Michigan Bar.
Bushnell saw brief service during World War I as a trial judge advocate. Upon the war's conclusion, he returned home to Michigan where he became a partner in a Detroit law firm. In 1933, he ran for public office as the Democratic candidate for the Michigan Supreme Court. He was re-elected for two additional terms in 1941 and 1949.
During the late 1930s and throughout the 1940s, Bushnell gained further prominence as a national mediator in industrial disputes. He was referee for the National Railroad Adjustment Board (first appointed in 1939). He was later appointed by President Truman to the National Railway Labor Panel in 1946. That same year, Bushnell chaired the Presidential Fact Finding Board on the matter of the airline pilots' strike. At war's end, President Truman asked Bushnell to serve as one of the judges of the Nuremberg war trials, but because of his heavy schedule on the state Supreme Court he declined the offer.
Throughout his life, Bushnell seemed most committed to, and took most pride in, his activities as a Freemason. Because so much of the Bushnell papers concern Freemasonry, it might be helpful to outline something of the organization of Scottish Rite Masonry.
An individual enters Masonry through Blue Lodges, where he is able to obtain three symbolic degrees: the first degree being "Entered Apprentice, " second degree, "Fellowcraft, " and the third degree, "Master Mason." Beyond Master Mason, the individual has the option of pursuing two branches of Freemasonry, York Rite and Scottish Rite. York Rite consists of Royal Arch Masons, Royal and Select Masters, and Knights Templar. Scottish Rite, the branch which Bushnell entered, includes the degrees from the fourth to the thirty-third. The administrative units for the Scottish Rite are called Valleys. Within the Valleys, there are four divisions: 1) the Lodge of Perfection, covering the fourth to fourteenth degrees (its presiding officer is the Thrice Potent Master); 2) the Council of Princes of Jerusalem, covering the fifteenth and sixteenth degrees (the presiding officer is the Sovereign Prince); 3) the Chapter of Rose Croix, covering the seventeenth and eighteenth degrees (presiding officer is Most Wise Master); and 4) the Consistory of Sublime Princes of the Royal Secret, covering the nineteenth through the thirty-second degrees (its presiding officer is the Commander-in-Chief).
The governing body for the several Valleys in the Northern Jurisdiction of the Scottish Rite is the Supreme Council, whose members are chosen from among the Valleys. From the Supreme Council in turn, there are chosen a smaller number of "Active" members who act as a kind of board of directors for the Supreme Council. There are at least two "Active" members in each state, one of whom is designated as the "Deputy" for that state. Heading the Supreme Council is the Sovereign Grand Commander, followed by a Lieutenant Commander and by the Grand Minister of State.
The governing body within each state is the Council of Deliberation, which is headed by that state's Deputy, and who in this role is designated as the Council's Commander-in-Chief.
With this background in mind, the researcher will better understand the multiplicity of roles which Bushnell played in Scottish Rite Freemasonry. He was "Raised" a master mason in Taylor Lodge No. 23 in Salem, Virginia in the early 1900s. Later, upon moving to Detroit, he entered Scottish Rite Freemasonry through the Valley of Detroit. He quickly moved up the Masonic ladder, becoming Thrice Potent Master of the Detroit Lodge of Perfection in 1925, and later Commander-in-Chief and Trustee of the Detroit Consistory, as well as a Trustee of the Masonic Temple Association.
During this time, in 1924, he was chosen Honorary Member of the Supreme Council and served as Sovereign Grand Inspector General, 33째. In 1934, he was crowned an "Active" member of the Supreme Council. Two years later, by virtue of his status as an Active member he was chosen Deputy for Michigan and Commander-in-Chief of that state's Council of Deliberation. In 1945, he was selected as Grand Lieutenant Commander of the Supreme Council of the Northern Jurisdiction; and in 1954, he assumed the position of Sovereign Grand Commander upon the retirement of Melvin Johnson. It was at this time that Bushnell decided to devote all of his energy to the Scottish Rite, and thus retired from the Michigan Supreme Court in 1955 before the completion of his third term. Bushnell served full-time as Grand Commander until his death in 1965.
As a Mason, Bushnell traveled widely and undertook a variety of responsibilities. In 1945, he journeyed to Europe as member of the joint White House Masonic Service Association mission. Among the many committees on which he served were the committees on Jurisprudence; Fraternal Relations; Constitution and Laws; and Rituals and Ritualistic Matters. Beyond fraternity, Bushnell's special interest in the Masons was its support of mental health research, especially in the area of schizophrenia. During his term as commander, Bushnell significantly strengthened this program through support of the Benevolent Foundation.
Outside of the Masons, Bushnell's other interests included involvement in the Michigan Democratic Party, the American Bible Society, the Michigan Board of Education, and the Sons of the American Revolution.
The George Bushnell collection, except for a small series of personal and political correspondence, and some speeches, concerns Masonic organizations and activities. The series in the collection are: Personal / biographical; Correspondence; Speeches; Topical files - Masonic activities; Name Files (personal and Masonic); Visitation Files; Foreign Chapters; Records of other Masonic officers; Miscellaneous; and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
African American freemasons.; Freemasonry.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Scottish Rite (Masonic Order)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bushnell, George E. (George Edward), 1887-1965.; Freemasons.
Contributors:
Carton, John J. (John Jay), 1856-1934.; Stevens, Frederic B.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal / biographical
  - Personal material (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Diary concerning trip to Europe on the status and needs of Freemasonry, 1945 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1921-1959, 32 folders (Box 1)
- Speeches
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Undated (political) (Box 1)
  - Undated (Freemasonry), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1925-1931 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - 1932 (campaign for Wayne County Prosecutor's Office) (Box 2)
  - 1932 ("The Partys and the Primary, " The National League of Women Voters) (Box 2)
  - 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - 1937-1940 (re. Frederic B. Stevens and related) (Box 2)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
  - 1940, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - 1940 (Masonic speech, Port Huron, Mich., January 29, 1940) (Box 2)
  - 1940 (George Washington speech, Chicago, Ill.) (Box 2)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - 1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - 1945 (Bible Society talk on the radio) (Box 2)
  - 1946 (Box 2)
  - 1948 (Box 2)
  - 1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 2)
  - 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1954 (Box 2)
  - 1955 1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 2)
  - Speech notes and related material (Box 2)
  - Speech programs and announcement of speeches (Box 2)
  - Allocutions as Sovereign Grand Commander 1954-1965, 12 volumes (Box 2)
- Topical files: Masonic activities
  The Topical files - Masonic activities series concerns committees and Masonic related organizations. Of interest here are several folders concerning black Free masonry (Prince Hall Affiliation) which threatened to become a very divisive issue between the Supreme Councils of the Northern and Southern Jurisdictions.
  - Allocation of 33rd degrees (Box 3)
  - Bay City Valley
    - General (Box 3)
    - Annual returns
      - 1938-1941 1943 (Box 3)
      - 1944-1946 1948 (Box 3)
    - By-laws of Scottish Rite Bodies (Box 3)
    - Financial papers
      - 1937 (Box 3)
      - 1938 (Box 3)
      - 1939-1942 (Box 3)
    - Statement of Rituals and certificate of election (Box 3)
  - Cerneau Freemasonry (Box 3)
  - Committees
    - Constitution and Laws (Box 3)
    - Fraternal (later Foreign) Relations, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - General State of the Rite-Detroit 1960 (Box 3)
    - History (Box 3)
    - History (re. Johnson's Masonic history) (Box 3)
    - Jurisprudence (Box 3)
    - Rituals and Ritualistic matter
      - 1937-1938, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1939 (Box 3)
      - 1942-1943 (Box 3)
      - 1944 (Box 3)
      - 1945-1952 (scattered dates) (Box 3)
      - Minutes and related material
        - 1941 (Box 3)
        - 1943 (Box 3)
        - 1944 (Box 3)
  - Deputy for Michigan: annual reports 1943 (Box 3)
  - Detroit Valley
    - General, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Annual returns
      - 1938-1939 (Box 4)
      - 1941 1943 (Box 4)
      - 1944 (Box 4)
      - 1945 (Box 4)
      - 1946 (Box 4)
      - 1948 (Box 4)
    - Benevolent Foundation (Box 4)
    - By-laws 1935 (Box 4)
    - Consistory papers, undated 1938, 1950-1953 (Box 4)
    - Masonic Temple Building Fund (Box 4)
    - Press relations
      - 1959 Fall Reunion (Box 4)
      - 1960 Spring Reunion (Box 4)
      - 1960 Fall Re-union (Box 4)
      - 1961 Spring Reunion (Box 4)
      - 1961 Fall Reunion, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1962 Spring Reunion (Box 4)
      - 1962 Fall Reunion, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1963 Spring Reunion (Box 4)
    - Press releases 1960-1962 (Box 4)
    - Report of Examination (finances)
      - 1948-1950 (Box 4)
      - 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - Statement of Rituals 1943, 1945 (Box 4)
    - Tax status (Box 4)
  - Ford, Henry (Special 33째 Ceremony December 5, 1940) (Box 4)
  - Grand Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons of Michigan (Box 4)
  - Grand Rapids Valley
    - General (Box 5)
    - Annual returns
      - 1938-1941 (Box 5)
      - 1943-1944 (Box 5)
      - 1945-1946 1948 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - 1936-1938 (Box 5)
      - 1939 (Box 5)
      - 1940 (Box 5)
      - January-April 1941 (Box 5)
      - May 1941-1942 (Box 5)
      - 1943 (Box 5)
      - 1944 (Box 5)
      - 1945 (Box 5)
    - Financial reports 1941, 1945-1946 (Box 5)
    - Statement of Ritual and certificate of election (Box 5)
  - International Freemasonry tour 1945 (Box 5)
    (see also diary in box 1)
  - Lieutenant Grand Commander (appointment) 1945 (Box 5)
  - Marquette Valley:
    - Annual returns 1938, 1939, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1950-1953 (Box 5)
  - Masonic Service Association
    - Undated 1945-1946 (Box 5)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 5)
  - Michigan council of Deliberation
    - Undated 1939 (Box 5)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 5)
    - 1942-1953 (Box 5)
  - African American Freemasonry (Prince Hall Affiliation), 8 folders (Box 5)
  - Obituaries (Box 5)
  - Salaries and retirement fund (Box 5)
  - Southern Supreme Council, U.S.A. (Box 5)
  - Supreme Council
    - General, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence January-March 1953 (Box 5)
    - Meetings
      - 1940 (Cincinnati) (Box 6)
      - 1943 (Buffalo) (Box 6)
      - 1947 (Cincinnati) (Box 6)
    - Declaration of Principles (Box 6)
    - George W. Graves painting 1951 (Box 6)
    - Tax Exemption (Benevolent Foundation) (Box 6)
  - 33째 nominations (Box 6)
  - 33째 nominations for 1945 (Box 6)
  - 33째 nomination for 1947 (Box 6)
  - Washington paper (Box 6)
- Name Files (personal and Masonic)
  - A (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Allen, Claude L. 33째, Deputy for Massachusetts (Box 6)
  - B (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Baynard, Samuel H. 33째, Grand Secretary General
    - 1940-1942 (Box 6)
    - 1944-1947 (Box 6)
  - Boyle, Orrin E. 33째, active to Supreme Council (Box 6)
  - Bushnell, George E. Jr. (Box 6)
  - Bushnell, Mary B. (Box 6)
  - C (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Cutler, Willard G 33째, Grand Treasurer General (Box 6)
  - D (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Denslow, Ray V. 33째, Grand Secretary-Royal Arch Masons of Missouri (Box 6)
  - E (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - F (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Foster, Orville H., Jr. 33째, active to Supreme Council (Box 6)
  - French, Carroll B. 33째, active to Supreme Council (Box 6)
  - Fulton, Clyde 33째, Deputy for Michigan (Box 6)
  - G (miscellaneous), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - H .(miscellaneous), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Hall, Carey B. 33째, Emeritus to Supreme Council (Box 6)
  - Harkins, Thomas 33째, Sovereign Grand Commander, South jurisdiction (Box 6)
  - Hey, Louis E. 33째, Active to Supreme Council (Box 6)
  - I (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Ivins, Benjamin F.P. 33째, Emeritus to Supreme Council (Box 6)
  - J (miscellaneous), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Johnson, Melvin M. 33째, Sovereign Grand Commander, Northern Jurisdiction (1945-1955)
    - Correspondence
      - Undated, December 1937, January-April 1938 (Box 7)
      - May-December 1938 (Box 7)
      - 1939 (Box 7)
      - 1940 (Box 7)
      - January-June 1941 (Box 7)
      - July-December 1941 (Box 7)
      - 1942 (Box 7)
      - 1943 (Box 7)
      - January-March 1944 (Box 7)
      - June-December 1944 (Box 7)
      - January-May 1945 (Box 7)
      - June-August 1945, October-December 1945 (Box 7)
      - 1950, 1951 (Box 7)
      - 1952 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - K (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - Keller, K.T. 33째 (re. Gourgas Medal recipient) 1952 (Box 7)
  - L (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - Lichliter, McIlyar, 33째 (Grand Prior of Supreme Council)
    - Undated 1951-1952 (Box 7)
    - 1953 1956 (Box 7)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 7)
  - Loyd, Robert L. (Box 7)
  - M (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - Mc (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - N (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - O (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - P (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - Pearce, Ernest L. 33째, Grand Treasurer General 1963-1964 (Box 8)
  - R (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Raschig, Frank Elmer 33째, Grand Secretary General
    - Undated 1947-1953 (Box 8)
    - 1956-1958 (Box 8)
  - Rork, Glen V. 33째, Active for Supreme Council (Box 8)
  - S (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Sayrs, Frank C. 33째, Emeritus to Supreme Council (Box 8)
  - Silverblott, D.M. (Box 8)
  - Skelton, Edward C. 33째, Past Active (Box 8)
  - Smith, James Fairbairn 33째, Editor-in-Chief of "Masonic World" (Box 8)
  - Spilman, Charles H. 33째, Grand Secretary General circa 1930s (Box 8)
  - Stevens, Genevieve (Box 8)
  - Strang, William F. 33째, Active to Supreme Council (Box 8)
  - T (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Turner, Henry C. 33째, Active to Supreme Council (Box 8)
  - V (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - W (miscellaneous), 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Wheeler, Edward W. 33째, Grand Lieutenant Commander 1954-1958
    - 1956-1958 (Box 8)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 8)
  - Y (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
  - Zaieck, Frank C. 33째, Active to Supreme Council (Box 8)
- Visitation Files
  As Sovereign Grand Commander, Bushnell was called upon to visit various Masonic lodges and to attend related functions. Since the Visitation Files included little more than hotel reservations and thank-you letters, it was decided to sample this rather extensive series. The series now consists of one random file for each year.
  - Pittsburgh 1954 (Box 8)
  - Toronto 1955 (Box 8)
  - Washington, D.C. 1956 (Box 8)
  - Kalamazoo 1957 (Box 8)
  - New York 1958 (Box 8)
  - Boston 1959 (Box 8)
  - Detroit 1960 (Box 8)
  - Kennebunkport, Maine 1961 (Box 8)
  - Toronto 1962 (Box 8)
  - Washington, D.C. 1963 (Box 8)
  - New York 1964, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Montreal 1965 (Box 8)
- Foreign Masonic Chapters
  Another series in the collection concerns Foreign Masonic Chapters. Included here are correspondence and other materials which Bushnell collected on the condition of Masonic lodges in Europe, during and immediately after World War II. This series is arranged alphabetically by country.
  - Argentina (Box 9)
  - Austria (Box 9)
  - Belgium (Box 9)
  - Bolivia (Box 9)
  - Brazil, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Canada (Box 9)
  - Central America (Box 9)
  - Chili (Box 9)
  - China (Box 9)
  - Colombia (Box 9)
  - Costa Rica (Box 9)
  - Cuba (Box 9)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 9)
  - Denmark (Box 9)
  - Dominican Republic (Box 9)
  - Ecuador (Box 9)
  - England (Box 9)
  - Finland (Box 9)
  - France (Box 9)
  - Germany, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Greece, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Guam (Box 9)
  - Guatemala (Box 9)
  - Haiti (Box 9)
  - Holland (Box 9)
  - Hungary (Box 9)
  - Iceland (Box 9)
  - Israel (Box 9)
  - Italy, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Korea (Box 9)
  - Manitoba (Box 9)
  - Mariana Islands (Box 9)
  - Mexico, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Norway (Box 10)
  - Nova Scotia (Box 10)
  - Peru (Box 10)
  - Philippines (Box 10)
  - Poland (Box 10)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 10)
  - Rumania (Box 10)
  - Russia (Box 10)
  - Scotland (Box 10)
  - South America (Box 10)
  - Spain (Box 10)
  - Sweden (Box 10)
  - Switzerland (Box 10)
  - Syria (Box 10)
  - T (Trieste, Turkey) (Box 10)
  - Uruguay (Box 10)
  - Venezuela (Box 10)
  - Yugoslavia (Box 10)
  - Foreign Masonic Publications, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Records of other Masonic Officers
  Although a personal collection, the George Bushnell papers are in part the archival records of the Masonic offices which Bushnell held. For this reason, the collection contains Records of other Masonic Officers who held offices into which Bushnell later moved. Thus, there is a small collection of papers for John J. Carton, who was Deputy for Michigan in the late 1920s and early 1930s, and Frederick B. Stevens, who was Sovereign Grand Commander of the Northern Jurisdiction in the 1930s.
  - John J. Carton 33째, Deputy for Michigan
    - Undated 1927-1934, 8 folders (Box 10)
    - Roy L. Hooker file (irregularly-made) Mason 1930-1932, 1934 (Box 10)
  - Frederic B. Stevens 33째, Sovereign Grand Commander
    - Undated, 1920, 1924-1933, 9 folders (Box 11)
    - Consistory and Masonic Temple Reports (primarily financial) (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous
  The collection concludes with Miscellaneous topical file relating to Bushnell's other activities and interests, and with Scrapbooks containing clippings pertaining to his career and Masonic affairs.
  - Topical file
    - American Bible Association 1944-1945 (Box 11)
    - Detroit Club (Box 11)
    - National Railroad Adjustment Board (Box 11)
    - Patriotic Women of America (Box 11)
    - Supreme Court, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Printed miscellanea (largely Masonic) (Box 11)
- Scrapbooks
  - 145th annual meeting of the Supreme Council, Boston, Mass. 1957 (Box 12)
  - Masonic activities 1954-1956 (Box 12)
  - Masonic activities 1950-1957 (Box 12)
  - Meeting of Supreme Council, 33째, Scottish Rite of the Northern Jurisdiction of the United States 1952-1955 (Box 13)
  - Political, Masonic, and other activities 1917-1948 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook concerning Masonic activities 1941-1954 (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook concerning personal and Masonic activities 1954-1965 (Box 13)
- Photographs
  - Portraits; photographs of Bushnell as part of Masonic groups, 3 envelopes (Box 13)